Guide to the Brookland neighborhood collection, 1979 MS2058
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Brookland neighborhood collection
1979
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
MS2058
1.5 Linear Feet
Collection contains materials such as the complete final draft of the book, "Images of Brookland," the original preliminary papers submitted by the students, the original cover photographs, the cover layout and the miscellaneous materials which were relevant during the course of the study. The book was first published in 1979.
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Historical or Biographical Note
This collection consists of material related to the production of the book "Images of Brookland" which studies the history and architecture of Brookland, a suburb of Washington, D.C. This study was undertaken for a course in the Urban and Regional Planning Department of the George Washington University, entitled "Inventorying Historical and Cultural Resources" and was conducted by eight graduate students in the Historic Preservation Program. It was edited by George W. McDaniel.
The purpose of the study was mainly to train students in the techniques of inventorying historical and cultural resources and to record such resources of a significant Washington community. Brookland was chosen as the subject of the study. The primary purpose of the study was the attempt to include people from the surveyed community as the main resources. This is one of the first studies that attempts to integrate developmental/architectural history with the community's social history and with substantial oral history from those associated with the community. The students participating in this study have also made a first attempt at correlating occupational status and the styles and types of architecture.
The area called Brookland evolved in the early 1870s, when the Baltimore and Ohio Railroad opened its western branch line in this area. The rail line was situated alongside the fine 1840 Greek Revival farmhouse, Brooks Mansion, home of Colonel Jehiel Brooks.
By the late 1880s, The Catholic University of America established its location just north of Brooks farm. Developers quickly responded to these expansions, creating a new Washington neighborhood beyond the central city and taking its name from Col. Brooks.
The Brookland neighborhood quickly emerged as community that included people of varied economic statuses. Near the larger homes of the more prosperous residents stood the more modest homes of middle- and working-class families. The styles of homes also varied: alongside elaborate Victorian houses were more simple Colonial and Craftsman structures. Unusual examples include John Louthan's Round House (1901) and Carrie Harrison's "Spanish Villa" (1909). Several houses in the 1920s were ordered from the Sears and Roebuck mail-order catalogue: the "Rodessa" model at 1518 Hamlin Street is similar to many modest bungalow style houses built in the neighborhood.
During the early part of the century, the city of Washington became increasingly racially segregated-and Brookland was no exception. Early on, Brookland had been predominantly white, and the area was largely closed to black residents through the 1920s. The anti-black riots that rocked Washington and other American cities in 1919 had little direct effect on Brookland, but the new segregation of the federal civil service under President Woodrow Wilson had more indirect effects. One sign of this shift is the fact that while CUA had earlier enrolled a number of black students, around 1917 the admission policy changed to include only white students. Only in the 1930s would the Brookland neighborhood-and the University--become more racially integrated.
In the early days, Brookland, a community of wooden houses – from Victorian Queen Anne to Craftsman-style bungalows – attracted government workers, a few Smithsonian Institution scientists, and people of many ethnic backgrounds who shared the Catholic faith.
Some examples of Brookland Residential Architecture, for the most part, middle-class residential housing, include: a Queen Anne style at 3425 14th Street, NE, The Rodessa, a 1920s Sears and Roebuck catalogue house at 1518 Hamlin Street, NE, and a Victorian cottage at 1351 Otis Street, NE.
Collection Scope and Content
The collection contains materials such as the complete final draft of the book, "Images of Brookland," the original preliminary papers submitted by the students, the original cover photographs, the cover layout and the miscellaneous materials which were relevant during the course of the study. The book was first published in 1979.
Collection Organization
Organized into five series: Final draft, Preliminary papers, Cover design, Miscellaneous, and Oversized materials.
Washington (D.C.); Brookland (Washington, D.C.); Photographs; George Washington University. Dept. of Urban and Regional Planning; George Washington University. Historic Preservation Program
- Final draft, 1979; MS2058 Series 1; 0.25 Linear feet (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains the final draft of the book "Images of Brookland" which was edited by George W. McDaniel. This includes the final draft of all the eight chapters which fall under part I and part II of the book. Part I of the book related to the history of Brookland while part II explained in detail the different architectural styles that can be found in Brookland. The series also contains the draft of the appendix and the photographic credits.
  - Title Page, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General note
  - Table of Contents, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Acknowledgements, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Introduction, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Map; Geographic Location of Brookland, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Part I, Chapter I: Establishment of the Brookland Community, 1887-1920, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Part I, Chapter II: Brookland between the Wars, 1920-1940, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Part I, Chapter III: Brookland in Transition, 1930s to 1950s, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Part I, Chapter IV: Contemporary Brookland, 1950s to 1970s, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Part II: Guide to the Architecture of Brookland; Overview of Brookland Architecture, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Part II, Chapter V: Typical Architectural Styles of Brookland, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Part II, Chapter VI: Unusual Architectural Styles of Brookland, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Part II, Chapter VII: Houses of Famous Brooklanders, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Part II, Chapter VIII: Four Historical Sites, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Appendix A: A Case Study of Residential Development; Square 4004 in Brookland, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Photographic Credits, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Preliminary papers, 1979; MS2058 Series 2; 0.25 Linear feet (Box 1)
  The material in this series relate to the production of the final draft which is contained in Series I. These are the reports given by the eight graduate students who conducted the study as a part of their Historic Preservation Program. The material has been arranged chapter-wise to correspond with the material in the final draft. While all the chapters are represented in this series, some of the materials are incomplete as they do not cover the full chapter. Some materials also include the editing done by the editor on the preliminary papers.
  - Historical Sketch of Brookland (used for part I), 1979 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - The Early Development of Brookland (used for chapter I), 1979 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Brookland Between the Wars, 1920-1940 (used for chapter II), 1979 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - The Transitional Period (used for chapter III), 1979 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Contemporary Brookland (used for chapter IV), 1979 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Typical Architectural Styles of Brookland (used for chapter V), 1979 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Unusual Architectural Styles of Brookland (used for chapter VI), 1979 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Houses of Famous Brooklanders (used for chapter VII), 1979 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Chapter VIII: Four Historical Sites (used for chapter VIII), 1979 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Cover design, 1979; MS2058 Series 3; 0.25 Linear feet (Box 1)
  This series consists of material relating to the production of the cover page for the book. This includes the cover photographs list and the original photographs used for the cover. The cover page layout could not be included in this series as the material was too large to fit in with the other materials. It has therefore been housed under the series of Oversized materials.
  - Cover Photographs List, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Cover Photographs, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Miscellanous, 1979; MS2058 Series 4; 0.25 Linear feet (Box 1)
  The materials in this series are the items which are relevant to the study and which have been helpful for the production of the final book. This includes the booklet containing the history of the Brookland Union Baptist Church and also some notes which contain the names and telephone numbers of the people who were contacted during the course of the study.
  - Brookland Union Baptist Church; History and 19th Anniversary Celebration, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Life History of Rev. Joseph A. Miles Sr. (Pastor of Brookland Union Baptist Church), 1979 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Names and Telephone Numbers of Brookland Informants, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Oversize materials, 1979; MS2058 Series 5; 0.25 Linear feet
  This series which is housed in an oversize box consists of only one folder which was too large to be fit in with the other materials of the collection. The folder contains the layout of the cover of the book, "Images Of Brookland", to which the whole collection relates to.
  - Cover Layout, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 1)